"Is Water Fluoridation Safe?"
Fluoride
had been found to be
a developmental neurotoxin
in rats and mice,
leading to learning
and memory deficits,
which led to an interest
in studying human populations.
Starting in the 1980s,
reports started appearing
in Chinese medical journals
that found correlations
between areas
naturally containing higher
fluoride levels in water
with lower intelligence
among children.
Dental fluorosis, the
fluoride-induced tooth mottling,
is widespread in China,
with more than
90 million residents affected,
often in small pockets
surrounding particular
small springs
or mountain sources.
Researchers took
advantage of the fact
that even adjoining
neighborhoods could have
wildly different
fluoride exposure,
setting up a type
of natural experiment.
Due to limited access
to Chinese journals at the time,
these studies largely
escaped the attention
of scientists in the West
until a meta-analysis
of 16 such studies
was published in English
in 2008.
"Fluoride and Children's
Intelligence: A Meta-analysis"
found that children living
in areas prone to fluorosis
had five times higher odds
of developing low IQ
than those living in areas
with little or no fluorosis.
So, here we were,
thinking dental fluorosis
was just a cosmetic blemish,
but it may instead
be a visual indicator
of intellectual deficits.
A subsequent
meta-analysis in 2012
including about 10 more studies
found that the average
intelligence gap between
high and low fluoride exposure
areas was about seven IQ points.
By far the largest study,
involving thousands of children,
it found that even
at fluoride levels below 1 ppm,
higher fluoride levels
were associated with
a large drop
in the chances of developing
excellent intelligence,
defined as an IQ
of 130 or higher.
Even very mild fluorosis was
associated with less than half
the odds of reaching
such a high IQ.
By now, there have been
more than 50 studies showing
an association between higher
fluoride exposure and lower IQ.
In the latest systematic
review meta-analysis,
90 percent of the studies
published in the last ten years
reported a link between
high fluoride exposure
and reduced intelligence.
However, serious caveats
are in order.
First, the fluoride
concentrations
in most of these studies
were well above
fluoridation levels.
In the 2012 meta-analysis,
for example, one study clocked
concentrations
as high as 11.5 ppm,
far exceeding the US target
of 0.7 parts per million
as well as
the average concentration
in the United States,
which is around 0.8 ppm
in municipal water
and 0.3 ppm in well water.
Now, to be fair,
the 11.5 ppm in the
meta-analysis was an outlier.
The average elevated level
was only about
two parts per million,
and most found
associated IQ decrements
below the EPA's upper limit,
its Maximum Contaminant Level
Goal of four ppm,
which is supposed
to represent the level
"below which there is no known
or expected risk to health."
Some studies showed
lower intelligence
with fluoride concentrations
even down at one to two ppm
with one estimate suggesting
the smallest harmful
concentration,
potentially shaving off
a single IQ point,
would be down around 0.3 ppm,
assuming you drink
four cups of water a day,
while others suggest
it's too early to be able
to calculate a threshold
for human neurotoxicity
due to insufficient
available data.
The second major caveat
is confounding.
Nearly all of the studies
to date have been performed
in rural communities
in countries like China,
Iran, and Mongolia.
Areas within these countries
with unusually high
fluoride levels
may be particularly
poor and underdeveloped,
since relatively
rich communities
may be more likely to invest
in higher-quality drinking water
that filters out fluoride,
if only to reduce
dental fluorosis.
High fluoride water may also be
more likely to be contaminated
with other neurotoxins.
Fluoride exists in water as
a negatively charged particle.
To maintain electroneutrality,
this may pull
into the groundwater
positively charged particles
such as aluminum,
arsenic, lead, or mercury.
This doesn't happen
in community water fluoridation
since the negative fluoride ions
are balanced out
in the water treatment process.
Finally,
most of the older studies
were cross-sectional
and ecological,
meaning they looked
at a snapshot-in-time
of group level data rather than
individual-exposures-over-time.
Just because a child with low IQ
lives in a high fluoride area
doesn't necessarily mean
they or their mom actually
drank the water, for example.
Ideally, we'd be able to measure
individual exposure levels
and then follow
the kids over time
to see if those
with higher exposure
really do grow up
with stunted intellects,
and that's exactly what
we'll cover in my next video,
entitled "Why I Changed My Mind
on Water Fluoridation."